all right
so how do I put images in my markdown
and links and you might not think that
they're related but in markdown they
look very much the same so I put these
together in the same video and let's
jump in and look at how to make them
hello from Greece um let's go ahead and
make a new document
here uh this's going to be MD Dash
whoops Dash uh images image how about
links we'll just call it image links MD
how about image Dash links I don't
care uh commit changes so we get a new
file again this is just kind of
saving uh we're cheating and using
GitHub for this kind of stuff um
somebody somebody already asked during
the break um you know the best somebody
suggested that the best way that they
had learned how to do markdown was to
use a renderer and a linter um which
will tell you if youve made mistakes and
it'll do you know real-time rendering of
that in another video I I talked about
St stack edit watch your eyes I talk
about stack edit already there are a
number of other ways to see rendering my
the reason I don't do that um is because
the number one place you're going to be
using markdown is going to be on GitHub
so I just want to say that again the
reason that we are using GitHub as our
place to do this use this rather you
know clunky editor is because it's the
most likely place that you're going to
be using GitHub and as we saw in the
inline formatting video you know bold
inside of italic doesn't work on GitHub
and it does work on stack edit in places
like that so so most people are going to
want to use markdown in a way that above
all is going to be compatible with GI
him then that's going to be up to you to
make a decision but since you know I'm
assuming nobody knows anything except
for GitHub at this point um that's why
we're here okay so once again let's do
the image link
um I am uh a link uh
to uh about this uh I would like to link
to uh skill
stack. uh or to a
specific uh boost uh page all right so
we start out with just a basic sentence
and you look at this and there's just a
sentence and then you can make the first
way you can do linking is you can just
put it in
HTTP now when I do this I'm going to get
some people are going to have problems
with this I'm like well what okay so the
linking the automatic linking of any
piece of text that starts with
https oh you didn't see that sorry here
you go um let me do that again so so
here we go this started out being I was
would like to link to
blah and because it has htps colon SL
slash this is detected to be a link this
could be mail to it could be any number
of different ways to link to things but
some of those other ones are not seen so
this is a a GitHub ISM it's a GitHub
flavor markdown ISM in other words
GitHub itself and many other renderers
will automatically detect a link by if
it begins with
HTTP um I have to tell you right now do
not depend on that that is a bad idea uh
that is explicitly not supported by
Common Mark uh or any of the original
markdown uh instead if you plan on
including a link directly like this en
encapsulate it surround it with angle
brackets that is the official syntax uh
and that will work everywhere right so
then you don't have to depend and by the
way that will also work with Mel to so
the other one doesn't right so the other
one the GitHub one only sees HTTP which
is completely stupid when you think
about it because there are lots of other
URL formats with schemas other than HTTP
so just get in the habit of using the
angle brackets the angle brackets around
a thing that you want you can use phone
a lot people don't know this right do
you guys know about the telephone link
yeah uh you can put the telephone link
there and you can you use that if you
use that up by the way if you use the
telephone link like this this was not
rendering that's really lame
that is supposed to be rendered oh wait
maybe it's not maybe it's not because
wait maybe it's like this let me see uh
555555 555 five I I mean oh my God it's
not doing it if you do the telephone
link um and it's on a phone when they
tap on it it'll it'll start up there
most most most phones will see telephone
numbers but if you want to explicitly
put a telephone number you can do that
and you can click on it and it will do
it um I don't know why this one isn't
isn't doing it right now but that is one
of the many uh things you can do so
there's the we'll talk about URLs and
schemas later when we talk about HTTP
but um https is is the way to to do that
um and you know I mean it could be
anything right 127.0.0.1
you would never do that but that's the
IP address um which we'll talk about so
that is these are called
explicit uh links and I'm just going to
tell you right now I have I have an
opinion on this personally I think every
Link in any markdown document you ever
make should be an explicit link that is
written out in text and let me justify
that statement I have been around long
enough to see documentation that was
said just click here have you ever been
you ever been to a web page raise your
hand if you've been to a web page that
says just click here right if you have
and and
the very exceptional case where someone
has printed that out and created a
printed document that says just make
sure you go visit here and that
hyperlink is now dead and so this is
this can this kind of dub Tails into a
rant against hyperlinking I am
dramatically against hyperlinking of any
kind right now um and unless it's you
know some really obvious thing and the
reason I think hyperlinking failed the
world um is because of this hypertext
does not
convey um people are taking screenshots
people are creating documentation people
on stack exchange have been explicitly
told make sure you print out your full
URL there people who write books like me
who do things and they they're you know
they're they're writing PDFs and stuff
like that those links some yes PDF
supports links but when you print the
PDF the link is gone and unless your
renderer is really smart it does not
know to include the URL someplace right
so the better not the better way to do
this is to do the same thing that a
bibliograph text would require when
you're doing a bibliography or you're
writing a formal document and it has
URLs in it you can not hyperlink you
absolutely are banned denied you know
forbidden from hyperlinking why because
that bibliography has to exist in many
formats including raw text and printed
media and in that case you're going to
lose that hyperlink hover over ability
and I'm just going to tell you when
you're talking about documents when
you're talking about the documentation
web we talk about the different versions
of the web in another video but when
you're doing documentation you want the
URLs to be visible there's only a few
cases where you wouldn't want that like
you were you were linking to an
application or you were linking to a
specific place on a specific document
but even then um if you were submitting
that as a formal document if your if
your documents is going on the web is
going to some somehow maybe be printed
or and if you're in education that's
often then you probably want to put a
link there so my preferred way so to end
that rant um because you need a web
browser to preview it that yeah that's
kind of what I'm saying um I am saying
that I don't like HTML because you need
a web browser to preview it and when you
are writing documentation you're not
necessarily always writing for the web
and that is a very unpopular opinion I
get it right somebody's going to take me
to task over it that's fine I I prefer
to write for all mediums and by doing
that that means not including HTML in
your document and not including links
that this should be its own video but
this is a good place to to to put the
rent um uh you know so I would say
something like um you know something
like this instead please make uh sure to
uh check out uh our uh website and then
I would do something like this 1 2 3 4
uh and then you know htps uh or however
you want to do do it uh
https skill
stack. and that's how you click on it
now you can do it however well I I I
that was stupid let me do this you can
be a bulleted list item you can do you
can do whatever you want and by the Line
This is just my reasons for doing this
um this this actually is now printable
it now gets screenshot and and a million
things like that um obviously the web is
full of a Wired Magazine comes to mind
of people to actually directly link to
different things another thing uh you
can actually read Tim burner's Le's um
uh justification of why hyperlinking in
the in the web particularly with slugs
is broken that's when the title appears
in the URL because now the content
cannot change change that URL um a a
good example of this is this is like
XKCD uh XKCD is actually my favorite
example of um of a website Who gets it
um the xkcds are are URL by um by number
and the number they're up here so that
the title can change at any time and
that is actually how Tim bers Lee wanted
it to work instead we have people
putting um you know actual titles in the
links and then the things get like this
you can't ever change it we kind of have
done that ourselves here so um but this
is what's wrong um what's wrong with
doing that I'm trying to just tell you
that if you didn't hear the whole rant
now that let me repeat what I just said
the reason that linking with using
hyperlinks like that um is like okay
I'll show you so here's the other way um
so uh or you can hide uh the URL by
going here right and then you can put
the link in here so this is this is the
other part of this video um and then you
put the period here and got to help you
try to copy that because you'll end up
copying the period um and you hit
preview here and you click on here and
it goes there right um I mean I I don't
need to overly dwell on the problem with
this right this is not going to work if
you have a URL that needs to be printed
or it needs to be screenshot or needs to
be visible in any way or you want people
to remember where the where the location
is right even when you hover over it and
this one's not set up to do that but if
you were hover over it show you where it
was going to go um you can definitely
link like this but my point is is that
if you use linking like this it should
sort of be secondary and it should not
be the primary way of redirecting
someone's attention for that kind of
thing I would suggest doing the
bibliographic way which is explicitly
putting the URL and and and doing that
um yeah uh yeah using a URL shortener is
is is another topic completely um we
won't get into that right now so the
actual syntax uh to include a link is to
put angle brackets around it okay that's
the official syntax if you don't do that
and you forget GitHub will put it in
there for you but nothing else will so
make sure you put the official syntax
which is the angle brackets around it
okay if you the other official syntax is
this um there this is really all you
need to remember so angle uh square
brackets with no space followed by a
parenthesis and then the link inside of
there this will become with hyperlink
text you can actually um use italics and
all kinds of stuff inside of here um
just like you would anything else uh if
you want to um and strictly speaking
there is another field here if you put a
space you put uh
alternate um text I think it is I don't
remember I don't ever use it though yeah
I can't remember yeah get play markdown
doesn't look like a support set at all
strictly you're supposed to be able to
put um something else there and and and
I feel like it's uh not doing it I don't
know if that's the official part of the
standard or not yeah it
is um yeah there it is see the alternate
text
there uh yeah you do have that notation
that's we're going to we're going to get
there next so that's next don't get get
ahead of me me too far
um okay so the most obvious way is this
way uh the second way of inline linking
is like this you can provide alternative
text that is a part of the standard by
the way so it does have to be in quotes
uh I never use that though um I mean I
can see reasons you might want to use
that but this is more likely what you're
going to see um uh uh or or let's see or
if you prefer uh to keep your text uh
more readable you can use inline
reference uh link syntax and this is
actually my favorite um and there's a
little bit of Divergence here as well
unfortunately um uh like this
right um and then you can have this be
uh
anything and then down here you can put
your link
and this is why it takes two passes to
render a markdown page because you have
to you have to rent you have to parse
the reference block before you can
actually resolve the URLs up above um so
it's kind of annoying for the people who
have to write compilers and renderers
but um but you know so be it right uh
skill stack.
iio um slash boost let's say that's
that's going to the Boost how about that
boost um and then you can put boost
here um and this is even this gets even
better um all right so see
now uh online only did I did I say
something
wrong keep your Tex oh was that you okay
yeah um where's let's see where so so
you see this this is kind of cool right
um that links to this thing now um if
you if you know the the
word uh you can do
this uh uh
HP I don't know
so uh uh or even just
this and this gets even this even
crazier so that goes to skill second you
see down on the bottom left they both go
to the same place uh uh or how about we
put a comma here this is I actually
really love this but this is not
supported
everywhere
um uh
or if on GitHub or a render
platform that supports it just this I
love this my absolute
favorite um because that also resolves
as well lot people don't know about that
one um this is spectacularly easy to
read um and you know uh for example um
for an example of the uh boost uh here
we go I just love this because it's just
so easy to read and you know it
immediately resolves it resolves
uppercase lowercase and it just makes
your text so readable it's just so
freaking readable um if you get rid of
the URL uh by I mean just making so it
doesn't match uh it will break the link
and now it's actually going to use the
brackets as it does here um I'm almost
positive this is a GitHub flavored ISM
uh this is also supported by pandoc it's
supported by uh every major thing but I
got to tell you it makes for some
absolutely
elegant uh documentation because when
you go into the source code anything
that's got a bracket around it that is
that also has a reference link uh and
then your your code is not you know is
not messed up um so here you know right
here I could put two skill stack if I
wanted to and then I could you know just
highlight the skill stack link it's more
it's more consistent with that it's
actually a lot more like asid do which I
really love which we'll talk about in
another video um so so that my friends
is is the those are the three main ways
of
linking um you I mean I guess that's
more it's like three-ish ways of linking
right so we have we have the regular
inline linking uh that's very visible
and obvious and prints and you know
copies and pastes with long with stuff
uh you know bibliographically sound if
you're making a paper that requires it
then we have the inline you know method
with the exclusive inline URL this can
get really really annoying for really
long URLs though I'm sure you know what
I'm talking about uh or you can use the
named tag version like this um or you
can just use this this is actually
supported uh the two brackets right
there that is supported by every version
of markdown um and uh and or you can use
uh A variation on standard markdown
which is pretty common to just drop the
extra brackets completely and just put
square brackets around and make sure
there's a reference link um that said
there is one caveat that I need to go
over when you're using reference links
so reference links are their own block
right and when you're doing
documentation it might not dawn on you
when you starting to make a single
document that you might accidentally
break those links right and so one of
the downsides of reference links um is
that you can easily copy this out let's
say let's say say that I copied this
this line right I cut it like that and I
put it in another document what happens
I got now have a broken unnecessary link
actually not in that case in that case
it would have been perfect right if I
copy and paste that link to another
another document the document stays it
has the link and the link doesn't break
right um if you are so the point the
point of this is very simple if you are
going to have links and if you're going
to have multiple documents right which
almost everybody is then the use of
inline linking uh despite how annoying
it is and how long I can get is going to
be more sustainable because you can copy
and paste that whole paragraph with dap
and Vim or something and then you can go
to another document and paste it and you
can be sure that the links are going to
stay there um you know I have gone back
and forth on this a lot because as you
can see having reference links makes for
a much more beautiful document um you
you know your links are all at the
bottom uh another downside of this is by
the way is if you have a long document
so a lot of people will have a rather
long document and they'll put the
reference link section at the very end
and it's annoying right because because
that reference link section is now uh
you got to go all the way to the bottom
of the document you got to change it and
you got to go all the way back up to the
top it does make for much more readable
text as you can see here but it makes it
much harder to maintain and I'm going to
make a suggest suggestion for you so
this this is a suggested middle ground
that I have practiced over time and I
actually really like it um this is my
own personal preference so you know
don't you know attack me for saying so
um but if you have um if you have a
paragraph or two uh you can actually put
the paragraph the links for the
paragraph right immediately after the
paragraph So then the paragraph stays
readable um if somebody who's coming
across your document wants to see it
they can see the reference they can see
it right here and they their eye is it's
in the same visual range they can see
that it goes with the paragraph and then
they can continue to scan on down
because there's no limitation as to the
number of reference link sections you
have in your document and they can pair
anywhere so if you do that then you're
more likely to do something like this
and copy and paste the two together and
then you you have a readable ask asky
text section
uh with your reference links that
travels with it that can easily be
changed and you can reuse that the
downside of that is obviously if you
wanted to use that boost in this case
for example what if I wanted to refer a
boost you know all throughout the
document in in five or 15 different
places I can't do it anymore right
because I'd have to have a redundant
copy of it and so it's up to you to make
the decision my my choice is is quite
frankly as I've said before to to to use
EXP explicit linking as much as possible
so that I can copy and paste it it goes
with a code um or to use the actual
inline links uh as somebody rightfully
complained um they are um it it is they
they're yeah inline linking is hard
having a separate link is I decoupling
the link from from the inline text is is
a thing um most people are going to be
using editors anyway so they're not
going to see a lot of that stuff but
argu that's arguably against the design
and the purpose of markdown which is as
you know quoted by grber said as text
that is as easy to read Source text that
is as easy to read as the rendered
version and I mean that's that's the
base premise of markdown and I believe
we've kind of moved past that and
markdown as just an easier way to do
HTML basically these days um I mean
these are some you know highly
controversial opinions but um in in my I
tend to put explicit links or I put
inline links uh unless it's a really
really long link and actually one of the
things that I regularly done in my zet
and I'll show you I'll find I'll find a
zet that does this um uh let's see Z all
zedel Casten so here's my zast I have a
bunch of notes in here um and you see
here I'll just put the links in there if
it makes sense to do that um otherwise I
will do um that doesn't have any these
are some old old entries they back when
I was not doing uh when I was wrapping
stuff see there's one that doesn't wrap
I'm trying to find one that
has um uh let's see let's do one it's on
AC I'm trying to find one that that has
a reference
section
um uh Peg how about Peg Peg has some uh
Peg and Peg Peg so much better than
previous version five what I was trying
to say okay so you see this I'll usually
put like um an inline URL like that um I
was trying to show you one that has a uh
I was trying to show you one that
has uh a related section so here we go a
lot of times I'll have like a related
section and then I'll put the the links
there fact let me show you when I make
one if I do bang bang links a um it'll
add you see what it did there it adds a
bulleted point and then I usually put a
related section like this and it has the
name and then it on a separate line it
puts the it puts the extremely long URL
so that it's always printed um that's
just my style but you know you're going
to have your own style and if there's
one thing that you should have the
latitude to be able to do whatever you
want it's definitely documentation so if
you're writing your own documents um for
your own searching and and and stuff you
know it's your it's your life it's your
decision you you do what works for you
um I spent so much time in the documents
in raw form and raw text form that I
really don't like URLs in my text I
don't mix URLs in my text at all ever um
if I have a URL I'll I'll put it down in
a related section and I'll copy it just
like I did with the title with it
printed out and then I'll say refer to
the related section for links about this
and I'll I'll mention it by you know
rhetorically inside of the inside the
paragraph That's My Style I I would
rather have that because I don't like
producing paragraphs that have a lot of
lot of noise in them in fact the only
noise I want in my paragraphs is
formatting period because that's easy to
understand and it renders in my text Bas
browser um uh let's see uh I don't
recall if you can have play markdown can
Auto generate TC no it
cannot um letic has fantastic autog
generation for table contest we're not
talking about LC we're talking about
markdown um so so that's where we are uh
so that's how you do markdown links um
the last thing we need to do is image
links and I'm going to go ahead and make
a separate video for image
links uh because it's it's kind of a
different thing and we'll talk about
images at the same time okay